James L. Holloway, Jr. Papers
James L. Holloway, Jr. Papers
1930-1964
Holloway, James L. (James Lemuel), 1898-
3.5 linear ft.
Papers of the American naval officer. Personal correspondence (1959-1964); memoranda and reports; articles and clippings; photographs; and other memorabilia.
149059
Biographical History
Admiral James Lemuel Holloway, Jr. (1898–1984) was a four-star admiral in the United States Navy. Born in Arkansas, he attended the U.S. Naval Academy in Annapolis and began his naval career in 1915 as a midshipman. Over the course of more than forty years in the Navy, he served as superintendent of the United States Naval Academy (1947-1950); as chief of naval personnel (1953 to 1957); and as commander in chief of United States naval forces in the eastern Atlantic and Mediterranean (1957 to 1959). After his retirement he served for a time as Governor of the United States Naval Home in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. As author of the Holloway Plan, he was an important figure in the establishment of the modern Naval Reserve Officer Training Corps.
Admiral Holloway was respected both by both his colleagues and those with whom he came in contact in the course of his duties. United Nations diplomat Rajeshwar Dayal described Holloway -- whose press nickname was "Lord Jim" -- as "a gentleman to the core," and in a Time magazine article one officer who served on Holloway's staff noted that "If he will ever be known for any command, it will be for his command of the English language."
[Quotations taken respectively from Dayal, A Life of Our Times, p. 358–359 and "Restrained Power", TIME Magazine, August 4, 1958]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The James L. Holloway, Jr. Papers consist of personal correspondence, invitations and other entertainment memorabilia, professional (military) correspondence-subject files, a small amount of manuscripts (reports, reminiscences, etc.), and general subject files.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent (incoming) or chronologically (outgoing). Invitations and entertainment memorabilia are arranged chronologically. Professional (military) correspondence-subject files and general subject files are arranged alphabetically by subject or title.
Related Material
has numerous collections relating to U.S. military history. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Military history; Holloway, James L. (James Lemuel), 1898- -- Archives.; United States. -- Naval Reserve Officers Training Corps.; United States. -- Navy -- Officers.; Admirals -- United States.; United States -- History, Military.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Memorabilia.; Memorandums.; Photographs.; Reports.; Admirals.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Per Columbia University Oral History Archive (source of the original), reproduction, citation, or quotation of this transcript requires the permission of James L. Holloway's heirs.
Inventory
- Correspondence, personal
  - Outgoing, 1959-1964 (Box 1)
  - Incoming, A-Z and unsigned (Box 2)
- Invitations and entertainment memorabilia
  - Invitations (incoming) and entertainment (outgoing), 1947-1964; undated (Box 3)
- Military (professional) subject files
  - Brussels, Belgium
    - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 4)
    - Non-correspondence, 1959 (Box 4)
  - Beirut, Lebanon: "Lebanon Operation"
    - Correspondence, 1958-1962; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Command directives and maps (Box 4)
    - Operation Blue Bat by Admiral Holloway, and Reports on Lebanon, 1958 (Box 4)
    - Reports and writings about Lebanon crisis (Box 4)
    - Photographs and miscellany (Box 4)
  - Chief of Naval Personnel
    - Master Recruiting and Retention Plan F 157, by Admiral Holloway, 6 Sep 1956; mimeographed (Box 4)
  - Naval War College
    - Harris Lanning Recommendation (Box 4)
  - Near East Trip
    - Reports, memoranda, etc, March 6-13, 1959 (Box 4)
  - Service Academies
    - Holloway plan (Naval ROTC) / Holloway Board, history of plan, criticisms, etc (Box 4)
    - Holloway plan (Naval ROTC) / Holloway Board, 1945-1963; memoranda and reports (Box 4)
    - United States Naval Academy, pamphlets (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - United States Department of the Navy
    - Correspondence (Box 5)
  - United States Fleet, Atlantic Squadron
    - USS Texas (Box 5)
  - United States Merchant Marine Academy
    - Advisory board, 1961-1963; correspondence with enclosures (Box 5)
    - [Miscellaneous], 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous, 1777-1845; 1928-1965,; undated; 3 folders (Box 5)
- Manuscripts
  - "Admiral James L. Holloway, Jr., U.S.N., Reminiscences", transcript of Columbia University Oral History project interview; carbon copy, with corrections (Box 6)
    Per Columbia University Oral History Archive (source of the original), reproduction, citation, or quotation of this transcript requires the permission of James L. Holloway's heirs.
  - Congressional statements by Admiral Holloway, 1955-1956; undated (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous reports and writings, 1930-1957; 2 folders (Box 6)
- General subject files
  - Biographical material (Box 7)
  - Magazine and newspaper articles, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Photographs (Box 7)
  - Souvenirs, programs, menus, admission tickets, etc.; 3 folders (Box 7)